<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lord General Cromwel's speech delivered in the Council-Chamber, upon the 4 of July, 1653. To the persons then assembled, and intrusted with the supreme authority of the nation. This is a true copie: published for information, and to prevent mistakes.</title>
            <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E813_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3114</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872279</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167951</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81007)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167951)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 124:E813[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lord General Cromwel's speech delivered in the Council-Chamber, upon the 4 of July, 1653. To the persons then assembled, and intrusted with the supreme authority of the nation. This is a true copie: published for information, and to prevent mistakes.</title>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber: [i.e. October] 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Council of State --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:167951:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Lord General CROMWEL's SPEECH Delivered in the Council-Chamber, Upon the 4 of July, 1653. To the perſons then aſſembled, and intruſted with the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nation.</p>
            <p>This is a true Copie: Publiſhed for Information, and to prevent Miſtakes.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeer 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:167951:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:167951:2"/>
            <head>The Lord General CROMWELL His Speech, At the Councel-Chamber, <hi>July</hi> 4. 1653.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppoſe the Summons that hath been inſtrumental to bring you hither, gives you well to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the cauſe of your being here. Howbeit, having ſome things to impart, which is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument drawn up by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and advice of the principal Officers of the Army, which is a little (as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:167951:3"/>more ſignificant, then that other of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: we have that here to tender you. And we have ſomewhat likewiſe further to ſay to you, for our own exoneration; and we hope it may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what further to your ſatisfaction. And therefore ſeeing you ſit here ſomewhat uneaſie, by reaſon of the ſcantneſs of the Room, and the heat of the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I ſhall contract my ſelf with reſpect to that.</p>
            <p>I have not thought it amiſs, a little to mind you of that Series of providence, wherein the Lord hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath diſpenſed wonderful things to theſe Nations, from the beginning of our Troubles to this very day. If I ſhould look much backward, we might remember the ſtate of affairs as they were before the ſhort, and that which was the laſt Parliament: in what a poſture the things of this Nation ſtood, doth ſo well, I preſume, occur to all your memories and knowledges, that I ſhall not need to look ſo far back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, nor yet to the beginning of thoſe Hoſtile acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that paſt between the King that was, and the then-Parliament. And indeed, ſhould I begin this labour, the things that would fall neceſſarily before you, would rather be fit for a Hiſtory, then for a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, at this preſent.</p>
            <p>But thus far we may look back: You very well know, after divers turnings of affairs, it pleaſed God, much about the midſt of this War, to winnow, as I may ſo ſay, the Forces of this Nation, and to put them into the hands of men of other Principles then thoſe that did engage at the firſt. By what ſtrange providences that alſo was brought about, would ask more time then is allotted me, to remember you of. Indeed, there are Stories that do recite thoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:167951:3"/>tranſactions, and give Narratives of matter of fact: but thoſe things wherein the life and power of them lay, thoſe ſtrange windings and turnings of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, thoſe very great appearances of God, in croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and thwarting the deſignes of men, that he might raiſe up a poor and a contemptible company of men, neither vers'd in Military affairs, nor having much natural propenſity to them, even through the owning of a Principle of Godlineſs, of Religion: which ſo ſoon as it came to be owned, the ſtate of affairs put upon that foot of account, how God bleſt them, and all undertakings, by the riſing of that moſt improbable, deſpicable, contemptible means; for that we muſt for ever own, you very well know.</p>
            <p>What the ſeveral ſucceſſes have been, is not fit to mention at this time, neither; though I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I thought to have enlarged my ſelf upon this Subject, foraſmuch as the conſidering the works of God, and the operation of his hands, is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part of our duty, and a great encouragement to the ſtrengthning of our hands, and of our faith for that which is behinde. And then having given us thoſe marvelous diſpenſations, amongſt other ends, for that was a moſt principal end, as to us, in this revolution of affairs, and iſſues of thoſe Succeſſes God was pleaſed to give this Nation, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that then ſtood, were very great things brought about; beſides thoſe dints that were upon thoſe Nations and places where they were carried on, even in the Civil affairs, to the bringing offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Juſtice, even the greateſt; to the bringing the ſtate of this Government to the name at leaſt of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:167951:4"/>a Commonwealth; to the ſearching and ſifting of all Places and Perſons; the King removed, and brought to juſtice, and many great ones with him; the Houſe of Peers laid aſide; the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, the Repreſentative of the people of <hi>England,</hi> it ſelf, winnowed, ſifted, and brought to a handful, as you may very well remember.</p>
            <p>And truely God would not reſt there, (for, by the way, although it be fit for us to entitle our fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and miſcarriages to our ſelves, yet the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the work may well be attributed to God himſelf, and may be called <hi>his ſtrange Work.</hi>)</p>
            <p>You may remember well, that at the change of the Government there was not an end of our Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, although that yeer were ſuch things tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as indeed made it to be the moſt memorable yeer (I mean, 1648.) that ever this Nation ſaw; ſo many Inſurrections, Invaſions, ſecret Deſignes, open and publike Attempts, quaſh'd in ſo ſhort a time, and this by the very ſignal appearances of God himſelf, I hope we ſhall never forget.</p>
            <p>You know alſo, (as I ſaid before) that as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of that memorable yeer 1648. was to lay the Foundation of bringing Delinquents to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo it was of the change of the Government: although it be true, if we had time to ſpeak, the carriages of ſome in truſt, in moſt eminent truſt, was ſuch, as would have fruſtrated to us the hopes of all our Undertakings, had not God miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly prevented: I mean, by that Cloſure that would have been endeavoured by the King, whereby we ſhould have put into his hands all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167951:4"/>that Cauſe and Intereſt we had oppoſed, and had had nothing to have ſecured us, but a little piece of Paper.</p>
            <p>But things going out, how it pleaſed the Lord to keep this Nation in exerciſe both at Sea and Land, and what God wrought in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> you likewiſe know, until the Lord had finiſht all that trouble, upon the matter, by the marvelous ſalvation wrought at <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs to you, I am very much troubled in my ſpirit, that the neceſſity of affairs doth require that I ſhould be ſo ſhort in theſe things, becauſe I told you before, This is the leaneſt part of the tranſaction, to wit, an Hiſtorical Narration; there being in every Diſpenſation, (whether the King's going from the Parliament, the pulling down the Biſhops, purging the Houſe at that time by their going away to aſſiſt the King, change of Government) whatever it was, not any of thoſe things, but hath a remarkable point of Providence ſet upon it, that <hi>he that runs may read.</hi> Therefore I am heartily ſorry, that in point of time I cannot be particular in thoſe things which I did principally deſigne this day, thereby to provoke and ſtir up your hearts and mine to gratitude and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now begin a little to remember you the paſſages that have been tranſacted ſince <hi>Worceſter</hi>-fight; whence coming with my fellow-Officers and Souldiers, we expected, and had ſome reaſonable confidence, that our expectations ſhould not be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, That the Authority that then was, having ſuch a Hiſtory to look back unto, ſuch a God that appeared for them ſo eminently, ſo viſibly, that even
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:167951:5"/>our enemies many times confeſs'd that God himſelf was engaged againſt them, or they ſhould never have been brought ſo lowe, nor diſappointed in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry undertaking: for that may be ſaid (by the way) had we miſcarried but once, where had we been? I ſay, We did think, and had ſome reaſonable confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that coming up then, the mercies that God had ſhewed, the expectations that were in the hearts of all good men, would have prompted thoſe that were in Authority to have done thoſe good things, which might by honeſt men have been judged a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn fit for ſuch a God, and worthy of ſuch mercies, and indeed, a diſcharge of duty to thoſe, for whom all theſe mercies have been ſhewed, that is, the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the three Nations, The true Intereſt of the three Nations.</p>
            <p>And if I ſhould now labour to be particular in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerating ſome buſineſſes that have been tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from that time, till the diſſolution of the late Parliament, indeed I ſhould be upon a Theme would be very troubleſome to my ſelf. For I muſt ſay for my ſelf and fellow-Officers, we have rather deſired and ſtudied healing, then to rake into ſores, and look backward, to render things in thoſe colours that would not be very well pleaſing to any good eye to look upon. Onely this we muſt ſay, for our own exoneration, and as thereby laying ſome foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the making evident the neceſſity and duty that was incumbent upon us, to make this laſt great Change, I think it will not be amiſs to offer a word or two in that, not taking pleaſure to rake into the buſineſs, were not there ſome kinde of neceſſity ſo to do.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:167951:5"/>
            <p>Indeed we may ſay, without commending our ſelves, I mean my ſelf and thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that have been engaged in the Military affairs, that upon our return we came, fully bent in our hearts &amp; thoughts, to deſire and uſe all fair and lawfull means we could, to have had the Nation to reap the fruit of all that blood and treaſure that had been expended, in this cauſe, and we have had many deſires, and thirſtings, in our ſpirits, to finde out wayes and means, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we might any wayes, be inſtrumentall, to help it forward, and we were very tender, for a long time, ſo much as to Petition, till <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, or thereabouts; we never offered to Petition, but ſome of our then Members, and others, having good acquaintance and relation to divers members of the Parliament; we did from time to time ſollicite, that which we thought (if there had been no body to prompt them, no body to call upon them) would have been liſted too, out of ingenuity and integrity in them that had opportunity to have anſwered our expectations; and and truly when we ſaw nothing would be done, we did as we thought according to our duty, reminde them by a Petition, which Petition, I ſuppoſe the moſt of you have ſeen which we delivered, either in <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, what effect that had is likewiſe very well known; the truth is, we had no return at all, that the ſatisfaction for us, was but a few words given us, the buſineſſe petitioned for, moſt of them, (we were told) were under conſideration; And thoſe that were not, had very little or no conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:167951:6"/>
            <p>Finding the people diſſatisfied, in every corner of the Nation, and bringing home to our doores the none performance of thoſe things, that had been promiſed, and were of due to be performed, we did think our ſelves concerned, we indeavoured as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came honeſt men, to keep up the reputation of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men in the world; and therfore we had divers times, indeavoured to obtain a meeting, with divers Members of Parliament; and truly we did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin this, till <hi>October</hi> laſt, and in thoſe meetings did in all faithfulneſſe and ſincerity, beſeech them, that they would be mindfull of their duty to God and man; and of the diſcharge of their truſt to God and man: I believe theſe Gentlemen that are many of them here; can tell, that we had at the leaſt ten or twelve meetings, moſt humbly begging and beſeeching them, that of their own accords, they would do thoſe good things, that had been promiſed, that ſo it might appear, they did not do them, by any ſuggeſtion from the Army, but of their own ingenuity, ſo tender were we to preſerve them in the reputation and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the people, to the uttermoſt. And having had, many of thoſe meetings and declaring, plainly that the iſſue, would be the judgment &amp; diſpleaſure of God againſt them; the diſſatisfaction of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the putting things into a confuſion: Yet how little we did prevaile, we well know, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve is not unknown to you; at the laſt when we ſaw indeed that things would not be laid to heart, we had a ſerious conſideration amongſt our ſelves,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:167951:6"/>what other way to have recourſe unto; And when indeed we came to thoſe cloſe conſiderations, they began to take the Act of the new Repreſentative to heart, and ſeemed exceeding willing to put it on, the which, had it been done, or would it have been done, with that integrity, with that caution, that would have ſaved, this Cauſe and the Intereſt, we have been ſo long ingaged in; there could nothing have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to our judgments, more welcome then that would have bin; but finding plainly, that the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it was not to give the people that Right of Choiſe, althought it had been, but aſeding right ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſeeming, to give the people that Choice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and deſigned, to recrute the Houſe, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to perpetuat themſelves: And truly having di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of us, ſpoken to, to that end that we ſhould give way to it, a thing, to which we had a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall averſation; which we did abominate the thoughts of, we alwayes declared our judgements againſt it, and our diſſatisfaction; but yet they would not hear of a Repreſentative, before it lay three years before them, without proceeding with one line conſiderably in it; they that could not endure to hear of it, then, when we came to our cloſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, then inſtead of protracting, they did make as much prepoſterous haſt, of the other hand, and ran into that extremity, and finding that this ſpirit, was not accoridng to God, and that the whol weight of this Cauſe, which muſt needs have been very dear unto us, who have ſo often adventured our lives for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:167951:7"/>it; and we believe is ſo to you, when we ſaw plainly that there was not ſo much conſideration how to aſſert it, or to provide ſecurity for it; and indeed to croſſe theſe, that they reckoned the moſt troubleſome people they had to deal with, which was the Army, which by this time was ſufficiently their diſpleaſure: when we ſaw this, truly, that had power in our hands to let the buſines go to ſuch an iſſue as this, was to throw back the cauſe into the hands of them we firſt fought with, we came to this firſt concluſion amongſt our ſelves, that if we had bin fought out of it, neceſſity would have taught us pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, but to be taken from us ſo unworthily, we ſhould be rendered the worſt people in the world, and we ſhould become traytors both to God and man: and when God had laid this to our hearts, and that we found the intereſt of his people was grown cheap, and not laid to heart and if we came to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of things, the cauſe even among themſelves, would even almoſt in every thing go to the ground, this did adde more conſideration to us, that there was a duty incumbent upon us, and truly I ſpeak it in the preſence of ſome that are here, that were at the cloſe conſultations (I may ſay) as before the Lord, the thinking of an act of violence was to us worſe than any Engagement that ever we were in yet; and worſe to us than the utmoſt hazard of our lives, that could be, ſo unwilling were we, ſo tender were we, ſo deſirous were we, if it were poſſible, that theſe men might
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:167951:7"/>have quit their places with honur: And truly, this I am the longer upon, becauſe it hath been in our hearts and conſciences, our Juſtification, and hath never yet been imparted thorow to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and we had rather begin with you to do it, than to have done it before, and do think in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that theſe tranſactions be more proper for a verball communication, than to have put it into writing; I doubt whoſoever had put it on, would have been tempted to have dipt his pen, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and wrath, but affairs being at this poſture, that we ſaw plainly and evidently in ſome Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call things, that the Cauſe of the people of God was a deſpiſed thing, truly then we did believe that the hands of other men, muſt be the hands that muſt be truſted with it, and then we thought high time for us, to look about us, and to be ſenſible of our duty. If I ſhould take up your time, to tell you, what inſtances we have to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſie our Judgements and Conſciences, that theſe were moſt vain imaginations, and things that were petitioned for, but that fell within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of our certain knowledge, and ſence; ſhould I repeat theſe things to you. I ſhould do that which I would avoid, to rake into theſe things too much; onely this, if any body were in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition, for any place of reall and finall Truſt, how hard and difficult a thing it were to get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:167951:8"/>thing to be carried, without making parties; without things indeed, unworthy of a Parliament. And when things muſt be carried ſo in a Supream Authority; indeed I think, it is not as it ought to be: but when it came to other Trialls, in that Caſe of <hi>Wales,</hi> which I muſt confeſſe, for my own part, I ſet my ſelf upon, if I ſhould inform what diſcountenance that buſineſſe of the poore people of God, there had, who had watchings over them, men like ſo many wolves, ready to catch the Lamb, aſſoon as it was brought out into the world: how ſignally they threw that buſineſſe under foot, to the diſcountenancing of the honeſt people there; and to the countenancing of the malignant party of this Common-wealth. I need but ſay, it was ſo; many have felt by ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it was ſo: who will better impart that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe to you? which for my ſelf and fellow offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, I think it was as perfect triall of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as any thing, it being known to many of us, that God kindles a ſeed there, indeed hardly to be paralel'd ſince the Primitive times, I would this had been all the inſtances; but finding which way their ſpirits went, and finding that good was never intended to the people of God, (I mean when I ſay ſo) that large comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them, under the ſeverall forms of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in this Nation; when I ſaw that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe was forgotten, to them all (though it was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:167951:8"/>very true, that by their hands and means, through the bleſſing of God, they ſate where they did) and affrayes, not to ſpeak it boaſtingly, had been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally brought to that iſſue they were brought to by the hands of thoſe poore creatures, we thought this an evil requitall, I will not ſay they were at the uttermoſt pitch of Reformation, although I could ſay, that one thing, the regulation of the Law ſo much groaned under in that poſture it now is in; there was many words ſpoken for it, we know many moneths together, was not time enough, to paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver one word called Incumbrances: I ſay, finding that this was the ſpirit and complexion of them, that though theſe were faults, for which no man ſhould have dared to lift his hand, ſimply for their faults, and failings, when yet we ſaw their Intendment was to perpetuate themſelves, and men of this ſpirit for ſome had it from their own mouths, from their own deſigns, who could not endure to hear of being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, this was an high breach of Truſt, if they had bin a Parliament, never violated, ſitting as free, and as clear as ever any ſat in <hi>England;</hi> yet if they would go about to perpetuate themſelves, we did think this to be ſo high a breach of Truſt, as greater could not be; and we did not go by gueſſe in this, and to be out of doubt in it, we did, (having that conference among our ſelves, whereof we gave accompt) we did deſire once more the night before the diſſolution, and it had been in our deſires, ſome two or three dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that we might ſpeak with ſome of the principal perſons of the Houſe, that we might with enuity o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:167951:9"/>our hears to them, to the end we might be either convinced of the ground of their principles, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, to the good of the Nation; or if we could not be convinced, they would heare our offer, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to prevent this miſcheif; and indeed we could not prevail for two or three dayes, till the night before the diſſolution; there is a touch of this in that our Declaration; we had often deſired it, at that time, we attained; there were above twenty of them who were members not of the leaſt conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for intereſt and ability, with whom we deſired to diſcourſe thoſe things, &amp; had diſcourſe with them; &amp; it pleaſed the Gentlemen Officers of the Army to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire me to offer their ſence to them, and indeed it was ſhortly carried thus, we told them, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our deſire to wait upon them, was that we might know from them what ſecurity, lay in the way of their proceedings, ſo haſtily with their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, wherein they had made a few qualifications (ſuch as they were) and how the whole buſineſſe ſhould be executed, we have no accompt of, and we deſired them they would be pleaſed, and we thought we had an intereſt in our lives, eſtates, and families, as well as the worſt people of the Nation, and that we might be bold, to ask ſatisfaction in that; and if they did proceed in honeſt wayes, as might be ſafe to the Nation, we might acquieſſe therein: when we preſt them to give ſatisfaction in this, the anſwer was made, that nothing could be good to the Nation, but the continuance of this Parliament, we wondred that we ſhould have ſuch a return, we ſaid little to that.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:167951:9"/>
            <p>But ſeeing they would not give us that which might ſatisfie us, that their way was honeſt, and ſafe, they would give us leave to make our Objections; We did tell them, that wee thought that way they were going in would bee impracticable, we could not tell them how it would bee brought to paſſe, to ſend out an Act of Parliament into the Country, to have qualifications in an Act to be the Rules of Electors, and Elected, and not to know who ſhould execute this; Deſired to know whether the next Parliament were not like to conſiſt of all <hi>Presbyters?</hi> Whether thoſe Qualifications would hinder them? or Newters? and though it bee our deſire to value and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of that Judgement, only they having been as wee know, having deſerted this cauſe and Intereſt, upon the Kings account, and upon that cloſure between them and the Neighbour Nation, wee do think wee muſt profeſſe wee had as good have delivered up our Cauſe into the hands of any as into the hands of intereſſed and byaſſed men, for it is one thing to live friendly and brotherly, to bear with, and love a perſon of another judgement in Religion, another thing to have any ſo far ſet into the ſaddle upon that account, as that it ſhould bee in them, to have all the reſt of their Brethren at mercy; Having had this diſcourſe, making theſe Objections, of bringing in Neuters, or ſuch as ſhould impoſe upon their Brethren, or ſuch as had given teſtimony to the Kings party, and objecting to the danger of it, in drawing the concourſe of all people, to arraign every individuall perſon, which indeed did fall obviouſly in, and the iſſue would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been, the putting it into the hands of men that had little affection to this cauſe. The anſwer again was made, and it was confeſſed by ſome, that theſe objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did lye; But anſwer was made by a very eminent perſon, at the ſame time as before, that nothing would
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:167951:10"/>ſave the Nation, but the continuance of this Parliament, this being ſo, we humbly propoſed an expedient of ours, which was indeed, to deſire that the Government being in that condition it was, and things being under ſo much ill ſenſe abroad, and ſo likely to come to confuſion in every reſpect, if it went on, ſo wee deſired they would devolve the truſt over to perſons of honor and integrity, that were well known, men well-affected to Religion, and the Intereſt of the Nation, which we told them, and was confeſſed, had been no new thing when theſe Nations had been under the like hurly burly and diſtractions, and it was confeſſed by them, it had been no new thing; we had been at labour to get preſidents to convince them of it, and we told them theſe things we offered out of that deep ſenſe we had of the good of the Nations, and the Cauſe of Chriſt; And being anſwered to that, nothing would ſave the Nation but the continuance of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (although they would not ſay they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate it) at that time leaſt of all.</p>
            <p>But finding their indeavours did directly tend to it, they gave us this Anſwer, that the things wee had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered were of a tender and very weighty conſideration; they did make objections how wee ſhould raiſe mony, and ſome other objections; we told them, that that wee offered as an expedient, becauſe wee thought better, then that for which no reaſon was, or thought would be given; wee deſired them, to lay the thing ſeriouſly to heart, they told us, they would take conſideration of theſe things till the morning, that they would ſleep upon them, and I think that there was ſcarce any day, that there ſat above 50 or 52 or 53. At the parting two or three of the chief ones, the very chiefeſt of them, did tell us, that they would indeavour the ſuſpending the proceedings of the Repreſentative, the next day, till they
<pb facs="tcp:167951:10"/>had a further conference, and we did acquieſce, and had hope if our expedient would take up a loving debate, the next day wee ſhould have ſome ſuch iſſue of our debate, as would have given a ſatisfaction to all; they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way late at night, and the next morning wee conſidering how to order that which wee had to offer to them, when they were to meet in the Evening, word was brought they were proceeding with a Repreſentative, with all the eagerneſſe they could; wee did not beleeve perſons of ſuch quality could doe it; a ſecond and a third Meſſenger told us, they had almoſt finiſhed it, and had brought it to that iſſue with that haſt that had never been before, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the things that did neceſſarily relate to due qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, as wee have heard ſince, reſolved to make it a paper Bill, not to ingroſſe it, that they might make the quicker diſpatch of it, thus to have thrown all the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Nation into the hands that never bled for it; upon this Account, wee thought it our duty not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, and upon this the Houſe was diſſolved.</p>
            <p>This wee tell you, that you may ſo know, that what hath been done in the diſſolution of this Parliament, was as neceſſary to be done, as the preſervation of this cauſe; and that neceſſity that led us to doe that, hath brought us to this iſſue, of exerciſing an extraordinary way, and courſe, to draw your ſelves together upon this accompt, that you are men who know the Lord, and have made obſervations of his marvellous diſpenſations, and may be truſted with this cauſe. It remains, for I ſhall not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you further with that that relates to your taking upon you this great buſineſſe, that being contained in this paper, in my hand, which I doe offer preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to you, to read, having done that which wee thought to have done upon this ground of neceſſity, which we know was not feigned neceſſity but real, and true, to the end the Government might not bee at a loſſe, to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:167951:11"/>end wee might manifeſt to the world the ſingleneſſe of our hearts, and integrity, who did thoſe things not to graſp after the power our ſelves to keep it in a military hand, no not for a day, as far as God enables us with ſtrength and ability, to put it into the hands that might be called from ſeverall parts of the Nation; this neceſſity I ſay, and we hope may ſay, for our ſelves, this integrity of laboring to diveſt the Sword of the power and authority in the civill adminiſtration of it, hath been that that hath moved us, to conclude of this courſe, and having done that, wee think we cannot with the diſcharge of our conſciences but offer ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, as I ſaid before, for our own exoneration, it hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been the practice of others who have voluntarily and out of ſenſe of duty diveſted themſelves, and divolved the Government into the hands of others, it having been the practice, where ſuch things have been done, and very conſonant to reaſon, together with the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to lay a charge, in ſuch a way, as wee hope wee do, and to preſſe to the duty, which wee have a word or two to offer to you. Truly God hath called you to this work, by (I think) as wonderfull providences as ever paſt upon the ſons of men in ſo ſhort a time, and truly I think, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the arguments of neceſſity, for the Government muſt not fall, take the appearances of the will of God in this thing, I am ſure you would have been loath it ſhould have been reſigned into the hands of wicked men, and enemies; I am ſure, God would not have it ſo, it comes therefore to you by way of neceſſity, it comes to you by the way of the wiſe Providence of God, though through weak hands, and therefore I think, it coming through our hands, though ſuch as wee are, it may not be taken ill, if wee offer to you ſome thing as to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that truſt which is incumbent upon you; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:167951:11"/>I ſeem to ſpeak that which may have the face of a charge, it is a very humble one, and he that means to be a ſervant to you, who are called to the exerciſe of the ſupreme authority, to diſcharge that, which he conceives is his duty, in his own &amp; his fellows names, to you I hope who will take it in good part, and truly I ſhall not hold you long in that, becauſe I hope it is writen in your hearts, to approve your ſelves to God only, this Scripture I ſhall remember to you, which hath been much upon my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11 and 12 <hi>verſe, Yet Judah ruleth with God, and is faithfull among the Saints,</hi> it is ſaid before, <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im did compaſſe God about with lies, and Iſrael with deceit,</hi> how God hath been compaſſed about with faſtings, and Thankſ-givings, and other exerciſes, and tranſactions, I think wee have all to lament; why truly you are called by God, to rule with him, and for him, and you are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be faithfull, with the Saints, who have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what inſtrumentall to your call, he that ruleth over men (the Scripture ſaith) hee muſt bee juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And truly it is better to pray for you than to counſell you in that, that you may exerciſe the judgment of mercy, and truth; I ſay it is better for you to do it, than to adviſe you to aske wiſdome from heaven for you, which I am confident many thouſands of Saints do this day, and have done, and will do, through the permiſſion of God and his aſſiſtance, to adviſe you; onely truly I thought of a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture likewiſe that ſeems to be but a Scripture of common application to every man as a Chriſtian, wherein he is counſelled to ask wiſdome, And he is told what is that Wiſdome that is from above, it is pure, peaceable, gentle, Eaſy to be intreated, full of good fruits, without partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without hypocriſy; and my thoughts ran thus upon this, that the executing of the judgment of truth, for that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:167951:12"/>is the judgement that you muſt have Wiſdom from above for, and that is pure, that will teach you to execute the judgement of truth, and then if God give you hearts to bee eaſie to bee intreated, to bee peaceable ſpirits, to bee full of good fruits, bearing good fruits to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to men as men, to the people of God, to all in their ſeveral ſtations, this wiſdom wil teach you to execute the judgement of Mercy and Truth; and I have little more to ſay to this, I ſhall rather bend my prayers for you in that behalf (as I ſaid before) and I know many others do alſo. Truly the judgement of Truth will teach you to bee as juſt towards an Unbeleever as towards a Beleever; and it is our duty to do ſo. I confeſſe I have often ſaid it fooliſhly, if I would miſcarry, I would rather do it to a Beleever than to an Unbeleever, perhaps it is a Paradox; but let us take heed of doing it to either, exerciſing inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to either; if God fill our hearts with ſuch a ſpirit as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> had, which was not only a ſpirit for the Beleevers among the people of God, but for the whole people, hee would have dyed for them, and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> to his Countrymen according to the fleſh, he could have dyed for them, truly this wil help us to execute the judgement of Truth and Mercy alſo.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing is, to deſire you would bee faithfull with the Saints, and I hope, whatever others may think, ought to bee to us all matter of rejoycing, that as one perſon our Saviour was touched with our infirmities, that hee might bee pittifull, I do think this Aſſembly thus called, is very much touched with the common infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Saints, and I hope that will teach you to pitty others, that ſo Saints of one ſort may not bee our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, but that wee may have reſpect unto all, though of different judgements; And if I did ſeem to ſpeak any thing that might ſeem to reflect upon thoſe of the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:167951:12"/>Judgement,</hi> I think, if you have not an intereſt of love for them, will hardly anſwer this faithfulneſſe to his Saints; I confeſſe, in my pilgrimage, and ſome exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes I have had abroad, I did read that Scripture often in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 41. &amp; 19. When God gave me and ſome of my fellows, what hee would there and elſewhere, which hee performed for us, and what would hee do? to what end? <hi>That hee might plant in the Wilderneſſe the Cedar, and the Shitta tree, and the Mirtle tree and the Palme tree together.</hi> To what end? <hi>That they might know, and conſider, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand together, that the hand of the Lord hath done this;</hi> And that the Lord hath created it, that hee wrought all ſalvation and deliverance, which hee hath wrought, for the good of the whole flock; therefore I beſeech you (but I think I need not) have a care of the whole flock, love all the Sheep, love the Lambs, love all, and tender all, and cheriſh all, and countenance all, in all things that are good; And if the pooreſt Chriſtian, the moſt miſtaken Chriſtian, ſhould deſire to live peaceably and quietly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, ſoberly and humbly deſire to lead a life in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſty, let him bee protected.</p>
            <p>I think I need as little adviſe you concerning the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpell, and incouraging ſuch Miniſters, and ſuch a Miniſtry, as be faithfull in the Land, upon whom the true character is, Men that have truly receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſpirit for ſuch a uſe, which Chriſtians will be well able to diſcern, and doe, men that have received Gifts from him that aſcended on high, and led Captivity Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, for the work before mentioned and truly the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Romans</hi> 12 when hee had ſummoned up all the Mercies of God, and the goodneſs of God, and hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of the foundations of the Goſpell, and of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall things that are the ſubject of his diſcourſe, in the 11 firſt Chapters, after he hath beſought them to offer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:167951:13"/>up their Soules and Bodies a living ſacrifice to God, hee beſeecheth not to eſteem more highly of themſelves than they ought, but that they would be humble and ſober minded, and not ſtretch themſelves beyond their Line, but they would have a care to thoſe that had received Gifts to theſe uſes there mentioned. I ſpeak not, it is farre from my heart, for a Miniſtry deriving it ſelf through the Papacy, and pretending to that which is ſo much inſiſted upon to be ſucceſſion, the true ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is through the Spirit, given in that meaſure that the Spirit is given, and that is a right ſucceſſion; but I need not diſcourſe of theſe things to you, I am perſwaded you are taught of God, in a greater meaſure than my ſelf in theſe things; indeed I have but one word more to ſay, and that is, though in that perhaps I ſhall ſhew my weakneſſe, it is by way of incouragement to you, to goe on in this work.</p>
            <p>And give mee leave to begin thus, I confeſs I never looked to ſee ſuch a day as this, it may be nor you, when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be owned as hee is this day, and in this world, Jeſus Chriſt is owned this day by you all, and you own him by your willingneſſe in appearing here, and you manifeſt this (as farre as poor creatures can) to be a day of the power of Chriſt by your willingneſſe, I know you remember that Scripture in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 110.3. <hi>The people ſhall be willing in the day of thy Power;</hi> God doth manifeſt it to be a day of the Power of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Having through ſo much blood and ſo much trialls as have been upon theſe Nations, made this to bee one of the great iſſues thereof, to have a people called to the Supreme Authority upon an avowed Account, God hath owned his Son by this, and you by your Willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doe own Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore for my part I confeſſe I did never look to ſee ſuch a ſight, perhaps you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:167951:13"/>are not known by face one to another; but wee muſt tell you this, that indeed wee have not allowed our ſelves in the choyce of one perſon, in whom wee had not this good hope, that there was Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and love unto all his Saints and people: And thus God hath own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you in the face and eyes of the world, and thus by your coming hither have you owned him, as it is in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43.21. It is an high expreſſion, and look to your own hearts, whether now or hereafter God ſhall apply it to you: <hi>This people</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I have formed for my ſelf, that they might ſhew forth my praiſe.</hi> It is a memorable place, &amp; I hope not unfitly applyed, God apply it to each of your hearts. I ſhall not deſcant upon the words, they are plain, you are as like the forming of God as ever people were, if any man ſhould ask you one by one, and ſhould tender a Book to you, you would dare to ſwear, that neither directly nor indirectly did you ſeek to come hither; you have been paſſive in comming hither, in being called hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that is an active word, <hi>This People I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> Conſider the circumſtances, by which you are called together, through what difficulties, through what ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, through what blood you are come hither; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor I, nor no man living, three months ago, had a thought to have ſeen ſuch a company, taking upon them, or rather being called to the ſupream authority, and therfore know your are called.</p>
            <p>Indeed I think, as it may be truly ſaid, that never was a ſupream authority, conſiſting of ſo numerous a Body as you are, which I beleeve are above 140, were even in the ſupream authority, under ſuch a Nation, in ſuch a way of owning of God, and being owned by him, and therefore I ſay alſo, never a people formed for ſuch a purpoſe (ſo called) if it were time to compare your ſtanding with thoſe that have been called by the ſuffrages
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:167951:14"/>of the people, who can tel how ſoon God may fit the People for ſuch a thing, and who would deſire any thing more in the world, but that it might bee ſo? I would all the Lords people were prophets, I would they were fit to be called, and fit to call, and it is the longing of our hearts to ſee them once own the intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt, and give me leave to ſay, if I know any thing in the world, what is there like to win the people to the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and love of God? nay, what a duty will lye upon you to have your converſation ſuch, as that they may love you, that they may ſee you lay out your time and ſpirits for them? Is not this the moſt likely way to bring them to their Liberties? and do you not by this put it upon God to find the time and the ſeaſon for it? by powring forth his Spirit, at leaſt by convincing them, that as men fearing God have ſought them out of their thraldome, and bondage, under the Legall power, ſo men fearing God rule them in the fear of God, and take care to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter good unto them; but this is ſome digreſſion. (I ſay) own your call, for indeed it is marvellous, and it is of God, and it hath been unprojected, unthought of by you and us, and that hath been the way God hath dealt with us all along, to keep things from our eyes, that what wee have acted, wee have ſeen nothing before us, which alſo is a witneſſe in ſome meaſure to our integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; (I ſay) you are Called with a high Call, and why ſhould wee bee afraid to ſay, or think, that this way may bee the door to uſher in things that God hath promiſed and propheſied of, and to ſet the hearts of his people to wait for, and expect? Wee know who they are that ſhall war with the Lamb againſt his Enemies, They ſhall be a people, called, choſen and faithfull, and hath in the Military way (wee muſt ſpeak it without flattery) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you know it, hee hath acted with them, and for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:167951:14"/>them, and now in the Civil power and Authority, and theſe are not ill Prognoſtications for that good we wait for; indeed, I do think ſomething is at the door, we are at the threſhold, and therefore it becomes us to lift up our heads, and to encourage our ſelves in the Lord, and we have ſome of us thought it our duty to endeavour this way, not vainly looking on that Prophecy in <hi>Daniel, And the Kingdom ſhall not be delivered to another people.</hi> Truly God hath brought it into your hands, by his owning, and bleſſing, and calling out a Military Power, God hath perſwaded their hearts to be inſtrumental in calling you, and this hath been ſet upon our hearts, and upon all the faithful in the Land, it may be that it is not our duty to deliver it over to any other people, and that Scripture may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling now to us, but I may be beyond my line.</p>
            <p>But I thank God I have my hopes exerciſed in theſe things, and ſo I am perſwaded are yours; truly ſeeing that theſe things are ſo, that you are at the edge of the Promiſes and Prophecies, at leaſt if there were neither Promiſe for this nor Prophecy, your coveting the beſt things, endeavouring after the beſt things, and as I have ſaid elſewhere, if I were to chuſe the meaneſt Officer in the Army, or Common-wealth, I would chuſe a godly Man that hath Principles, eſpecially where truſt is to be committed, becauſe I know where to have a man that hath Principles; I beleeve if any man of you ſhould chuſe a Servant, you would do ſo, and I would all our Magiſtrates were ſo choſen, that may be ſome effects of this; it is our duty to chuſe men that fear the Lord, to praiſe the Lord, yea ſuch as the Lord forms for himſelf, andhe expects not praiſes from others; this being ſo, it puts me in minde of another Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. which indeed is a glorious Prophecy, and I am perſwaded of the Goſpel, or it may be of the <hi>Jews;</hi> alſo there it is Propheſied, <hi>He will bring his people again out of the depths of the Sea, as once he led</hi> Iſrael <hi>through the red Sea;</hi> and it may be ſome do think God is bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Jews</hi> home to their ſtation from the Iſles of the Sea, ſurely when God ſets up the glory of the Goſpel-Church, it ſhall be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people out of deep waters, out of the multitude of waters; ſuch are his people, drawn out of the multitudes of the Nations, and people of the world. And that Pſalm will be very glorious in many other parts of it, <hi>When he gave the word, great was the company, of them that publiſhed it; Kings of the Armies did fly apace,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:167951:15"/>and ſhe that tarried at home divided the ſpoyl, and although ye have lain among the Pots, yet ſhall ye be as the wings of a Dove covered with ſilver, and her feathers with yellow gold.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the triumph of that Pſalm is exceeding high and great, and God is accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhing it; and the cloze of it, that cloſeth with my heart and I am perſwaded will with yours alſo; That <hi>God ſhakes Hills and Mountains, and they reel,</hi> and God hath a Hill too, <hi>and his hill is as the hill of</hi> Baſhan, <hi>and the Chariots of God are twenty thouſand of Angels, and God will dwell upon this hill for ever.</hi> Truly I am ſorry that I have troubled you, in ſuch a place of heat as this is, ſo long; all that I have to ſay in mine own name, and in the names of my Fellow Officers (who have joyned with me in this Work) That we ſhall commend you to the Grace of God, and to the guidance of his Spirit, having thus farre ſerved you (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in it) we are, as we hope, and ſhall be, ready in our ſtations, according as the Providence of God ſhall lead us, to be ſubſervient to the Work of God, and the Authority (which we reckon) God hath ſet over us. And although we have no For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal thing to preſent you with, to which the hands and outward vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible expreſſions of the hearts of the Officers of the three Nations are ſet, yet we may ſay for them, and we may ſay alſo with confidence for our Brethren at Sea, with whom neither in <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> nor at Sea hath any Artifice been uſed to perſwade their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations to this work; yet we can ſay, That their conſent and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections hath flowed in to us from all parts beyond our expectations, and we are confident we may ſay with all confidence, That we have had their approbations, and full conſent, unſought indeed to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work, ſo that you have their hearts and affections in this; and not only they, but we have very many Papers from the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God, throughout the Nation, wonderfully both approving what hath been done in removing Obſtacles, and approving what we have done in this very thing. And having ſaid this I ſhall trouble you no more, but if you will be pleaſed that this Inſtrument may be read, which I have Signed by the advice of the Councel of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, we ſhall then leave you to your own thoughts, and to the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of God, to order and diſpoſe of your ſelves for further Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings as you ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
